Guide to the Houston Philosophical Society Records, 1808-2004 UA 076
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Houston Philosophical Society Records
1808-2004
1940-2004
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Houston Philosophical Society.
UA 076
8.5 Linear Feet (17 boxes)
The Houston Philosophical Society was established in 1920 at the University Club in downtown Houston to bring together the intellectual community both on and off campus. Many members of the Rice University community have been invlode as leaders in the society. These records consist of minutes from the Executive Committee and general meetings, notices to members, treasurer's reports and other financial records, rosters and directories, new member nominations, constitutions and procedure guidelines.
Historical Sketch
The first meeting of the Houston Philosophical Society was held on January 18, 1920 at the University Club in downtown Houston. It was organized to bring together the intellectual community both on and off campus. Its purpose was to "stimulate interest in modern developments in science and philosophy." The word "philosophical" is used in its broadest sense and members of the society represent all departments of the arts, sciences, and letters.
At that first meeting Professor H. A. Wilson was elected as president, Professor G. C. Evans as secretary, and Mr. S. G. McCann (the registrar at Rice) as treasurer. Three additional members were elected to serve on the executive council: Professors C. W. Heaps, H. B. Weiser, and R. A. Tsanoff. The persons listed here, whose main work was respectively in physics, mathematics, history, chemistry, and philosophy, indicate the wide range of interests that has characterized the Society from the beginning.
The monthly meetings held during the academic year normally consist of a dinner, followed by a business session and then the address of the evening by either a member of the Society or an invited guest speaker. Time is reserved for questions or discussion after the address.
The members of the Society are elected based on their high intellectual and professional achievements. Originally an all male organization, in 1987 the bylaws were changed so that they did not imply that one had to be male to be a member. By the next year several women had been elected. Today the Society has no gender or racial restrictions and has a maximum membership of 240 members divided into eight sections as follows:
Astronomy, Engineering, and Mathematics
Biochemistry, Biology, Chemistry, Geology, and Physics
Medicine
Business and Economics
Education, Health, and Physical Education, Philosophy, Psychology, Religion, and Social Science
History, Journalism, Language, Literature, and Library Science
Architecture, Fine Arts, Music, and Theater
Government and Law
Members pay annual dues but are exempt if they have achieved Life Membership status. This membership is granted to active members of the Society who are over the age of 70, and who have been active members for a period of at least 10 years.
Parts excerpted from the 1998 Houston Philosophical Society Directory/Handbook
Scope and Contents
The Houston Philosophical Society Records consist of minutes from the Executive Committee and general meetings, notices to members, treasurer's reports and other financial records, rosters and directories, new member nominations, constitutions and procedure guidelines. There is one roll of microfilm minutes for 1964-May 1974. One binder belonging to President W. T. Cannady, 1998-99 is included. These documents are divided in to 7 series as identified below.
Until April 2000, the documents were filed by subject, i. e., Minutes, Notices, Treasurer's Report, etc. in chronological order. Beginning April 2000 the documents are kept together by meeting number and date. A new series was started at that point.
Access Restrictions
This material is open for research.
Stored offsite at the Library Service Center and require 24-hour notice for retrieval. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at 713-348-2586 or woodson@rice.edu for more information.
Box 17 stored onsite at the Woodson Research Center.
Acquisition Information
These records have been placed with the Woodson Research Center by various members of the Society over a number of years-S. W. Higginbotham, K. Kolenda, John A. S. Adams, John Boles, Harold Raley received in 1974, 6/1984, 10/1988, 2/1989, 6/1992, 9/1993, 11/1993, 7/1995, 6/1996, 12/1996 and 2/2003.
Index Terms
Subjects
Education
Document Types
speeches; minutes (administrative records); directories; corrrespondence; constitutions
Subjects (Corporations)
Houston Philosophical Society.
- Series I: Notices / Correspondence, 1928-2001, 229583
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains Notices, for both the Executive and business meetings. Some attachments to these notices may include new member nominations. Also filed here are correspondence files and meeting reservations.
  - Notices, 1928-44; 229593 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Notices, 1945-58; 229592 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Notices, 1971-81; 229591 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Notices, 1982-92; 229590 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Notices, 1993-99*; 229589 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    General note
    * See individual meeting files for latest records
  - Notices, Executive Committee, 1971-96; 229588 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1971-2001; 229587 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, Executive Committee, 1986-94; 229586 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, Executive Committee, 2000-; 229585 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Related Archival Materials note
    See also "Minutes and related material, Executive Committee" in Series VI for email correspondence specifically relating to monthly Executive Committee meetings.
  - Meeting reservations, 1988-March 2000*; 229584 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Series II: Membership, 1940-2000, 229564
  Contains membership rosters, directories and handbooks, change forms and membership nominations/ supporting letters.
  - Membership nominations/supporting letters, 1988-90; 229582 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Membership nominations/supporting letters, 1991-92; 229581 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Membership nominations/supporting letters, 1993-2001; 229580 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Membership nominations/supporting letters, 2002-2003; 229579 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Membership nominations/supporting letters, 2004; 229578 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Membership nominations/supporting letters, 2005-2009; 229577 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Permanent record of membership, c. 1952; 229576 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Membership rosters, 1940-73; 229575 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Membership rosters, 1980's; 229574 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Membership rosters, 1990's; 229573 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Membership rosters, 2000's; 229572 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Executive Committee rosters, 229571 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Membership directories, 1965-2007; 229570 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence concerning membership, 1996-1999; 229569 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence concerning membership, 2002-2005; 229568 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence concerning membership, 2006-; 229567 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Section Membership Summary, January 17, 2002; 229566 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Membership Committee, 2006; 229565 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Series III: Financial, 1922-1996, 229552
  Contains bills and financial records, various financial journals and Treasurer's reports. There is a personal file from Treasurer Fraser A. McAlpine.
  - Bills - Faculty Club, 1984-94; 229563 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Bills - General, 1983-88; 229562 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Check register, 1985-89; 229561 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Dues records, 229560 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Financial Statements, 1983-89; 229559 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Treasurer's reports, 1973-96* **; 229558 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    ** See 1998-March 2000 Executive Committee Minutes
  - Treasurer Fraser A. McAlpine personal file, 1988-90; 229557 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Treasurer's journal, 1922-40; 229556 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Bank journal, 1922-46; 229555 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Treasury, 2005-2006; 229554 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Financial (General), 229553 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Series IV: General, 1808-2001, 229546
  Contains governing documents, such as the Society Constitution and procedure guidelines. There is also a copy of the Philosophical Society of Texas Constitution.
  - Constitution (copy), Philosophical Society of Texas, 1807, 1837; Proceedings, 1955; 229551 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Constitution, c. 1990; 229550 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Constitution and Bylaws, 2005-2008; 229549 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Practices, Procedure, and Calendar, 1999/2000; 229548 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Secretary's duties, c. 2001; 229547 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Series V: President's Binder, 1998-1999, 229544
  Contains copy of binder belonging to President W. T. Cannady, 1998-99.
  - W. T. Cannady, President, 1998-1999; 229545 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Series VI: Meeting Minutes, 1920-2000, 229524
  Contains minutes of the Executive Committee meetings as well as the business meetings, going back to 1920. Some of the minutes are bound into journals. There are some summaries of the speakers' addresses with the business meeting minutes.
  - Minutes book, Executive Committee, 1920-50; 229543 (Box 8, Item 1)
  - Minutes book (photocopies), Executive Committee, 1920-1950; 229542 (Box 8, Item 2)
  - Minutes book, 1920-42; 229541 (Box 8, Item 3)
  - Minutes book, 1942-57; 229540 (Box 8, Item 4)
  - Minutes book, photocopies, 1920-64; 229539 (Box 8, Item 5)
  - Minutes book, 1957-1964; 229538 (Box 8, Item 6)
  - Minutes book, 1964-74; 229537 (Box 9, Item 1)
  - Minutes book (photocopies), 1964-1974; 229536 (Box 9, Item 2)
  - Microfilm of minutes, 1964-1974; 229535 (Box 9, Item 3)
  - Minutes book, 1974-1977, 229534 (Box 9, Item 4)
  - Minutes, 1977-83; 229533 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 1984-87; 229532 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1988-90; 229531 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 1991-93; 229530 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 1994-96; 229529 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Minutes and related material, 1997-1999*; 229528 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    *see individual meeting files for latest records
  - Minutes and related material, Executive Committee, 1986-2000; 229527 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Minutes and related material, Executive Committee, 2001-2003; 229526 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Minutes and related material, Executive Committee, 2004-2009; 229525 (Box 11, Folder 1)
- Series VII: Meeting Records, 2000-2004, 229498
  Contains minutes of the Executive Committee meetings as well as the business meetings, going back to 1920. Includes Minutes, Executive Committee, Notices, Treasurer's Reports, etc. Some of the minutes are bound into journals. There are some summaries of the speakers' addresses with the business meeting minutes.
  - Meeting No. 565, January 20, 2000; 229523 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Meeting No. 566, February 17, 2000; 229522 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Meeting No. 567, March 16, 2000; 229521 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Meeting No. 568, April 20, 2000; 229520 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Meeting No. 569, Sept. 21, 2000; 229519 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Meeting No. 570, October 19, 2000; 229518 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Meeting No. 571, November 16, 2000; 229517 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Meeting No. 572, January 18, 2001; 229516 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Meeting No. 573, February 15, 2001; 229515 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Meeting No. 574, March 15, 2001; 229514 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Meeting No. 575, April 19, 2001; 229513 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Meeting No. 576, September 20, 2001; 229512 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Meeting No. 577, Oct. 18, 2001; 229511 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Meeting No. 578, Nov. 15, 2001; 229510 (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Meeting No. 579, January 17, 2002; 229509 (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Meeting No. 580, Feb. 21, 2002; 229508 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Meeting No. 581, March 21, 2002; 229507 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Meeting No. 582, April 18, 2002; 229506 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Meeting No. 583, September 19, 2002; 229505 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Meeting No. 584, October 17, 2002; 229504 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Meeting No. 585, November 21, 2002; 229503 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Meetings, 2003, No's 586-588, 590-592, 229502 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Meetings, 2004, No's 593, 595, 596, 599, 229501 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Meetings, 2005; 229500 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Meetings, 2006-2009; 229499 (Box 12, Folder 10)
- Series VIII: Addenda materials, 1920-2010, 229447
  - Analyses, 229497 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Secretary's notebook, 1998-99, 229496 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Secretary's notebook, 1999-2000, 229495 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Secretary's notebook, 2000-01, 229494 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - President's notebook, 2001-02, 229493 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - List of speakers, 1981-1998; 229492 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Speaker, Robert L. Patten, Nov. 20, 2003; 229491 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Speakers, 2006-2007; 229490 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Speakers, 2008-2009; 229489 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Audit Committee, 229488 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Association Management Contractors (AMC); Administrative Services Agreement, 2006; 229487 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Timelines, 229486 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Website, 229485 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - "HPS Files" CD-ROM, 229484 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - HPS, Mailbox 540472 (Key), 229483 (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Note Fragments, 229482 (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Constitution and bylaws, 229481 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Membership directory, 2008-09, 229480 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Executive Committee, 2005-08, 229479 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Executive Committee minutes, 2009-10, 229478 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Executive Committee, 2012, 229477 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Dinner meeting minutes, 2007-08, 229476 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Secretaries file-minutes, 229475 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Secretaries files-timeline, 229474 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Secretaries file-Presidents handbook, 229473 (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Secretaries file-Business, 229472 (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Secretaries file-Correspondence, 229471 (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Secretaries file-Notices, 229470 (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Secretaries file-Directory, 229469 (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - Secretaries file-Section information, 229468 (Box 16, Folder 14)
  - Section roster/members, 2009-10, 229467 (Box 16, Folder 15)
  - Proposed new section designations, 229466 (Box 16, Folder 16)
  - Website, 229465 (Box 16, Folder 17)
  - Member nomination information, 229464 (Box 16, Folder 18)
  - New member ballots, 11-16-2006, 229463 (Box 16, Folder 19)
  - New member ballots, April 2007, 229462 (Box 16, Folder 20)
  - Schedules and speakers, 2008-11, 229461 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Proposed speakers, 2007-11, 229460 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Summary of financial activitiy, 2007-10, 229459 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Funds reports, 2006-07, 229458 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Bank statements, 2006-07, 229457 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Inventories/payments, 2006-07, 229456 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Audit Committee, 229455 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Treasurer's forms, 229454 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Mendelson, John, "Targeting Abhorrent Behavior...", 229453 (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Hudspeth, C.M., "Variation on a Theme of Natural Law", 229452 (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - Glowinski, Ronald, "Mathematics & Mathematicians", 229451 (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - Fall 2000 pamphlet, 229450 (Box 17, Folder 12)
  - Notes, 229449 (Box 17, Folder 13)
  - Cohen House [Rice Univ.] card, 229448 (Box 17, Folder 14)